Good to see you. Today's דף daf is קכ"ז, Kuf Chaf Zayin,
127, also happy שלושת ימי הגבלה. Shlosha Yemei Hagbala. We pick up,
we had started a new משנה, mishna, and the משנה mishna shifted
from the
120 and 7.
Right exactly, the years of שרה אמנו. Sarah Imeinu. Okay, so we
our the משנה mishna from yesterday's דף daf moved from the actual
the double portion per se to identifying who the firstborn son is,
and that led to the גמרא's Gemara discussion here. A statement of,
who was it initially, who made the statement?
רב אמי Rav Ami said that if a טומטום, tumtum, if a
child is born with the genitalia have not descended or maybe there's
a skin covering it up and then afterwards they descended or the
skin tore and you saw that it was a בן, ben, that
he does not get a double portion because it says והיה הבן
הבכור, vehaya haben habachor, when the child is born it has to
be already a בן, ben, it has to be noticeable as a
בן. ben. And then the גמרא Gemara applied that idea to a
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh and then also to, it would
also be true in a, there's a like a complicated math, but
if a second boy had that situation it wouldn't impact on the
בכור's bachor size of the בכור's bachor portion. So all of these
cases in which a child who has the status of a son
or of a boy or whatever and has certain halachic implications has
to be that way from the moment of birth, or noticeable that
way. So now we pick up, we'll read a little bit from
yesterday from the top of קכ"ז עמוד א', Kuf Chaf Zayin Amud
Aleph, it says like this, three lines from the
top: רב שיזבי אמר, Rav Shizvi amar, רב שיזבי Rav Shizvi says:
אף אינו נימול לשמונה. af eino nimal lishmona. If a baby boy
is born on the eighth day but at that stage it was
a טומטום, tumtum, you couldn't identify male or female, then it becomes
identifiable before the eighth day,
you do not have a ברית מילה brit milah on the eighth
day. It doesn't mean you don't have it, you would have it
on the eighth day, but it means the eighth day does not
have that weight in the sense that it would override שבת. Shabbat.
Okay? דאמר קרא De'amar kra because the פסוק pasuk says: אישה כי
תזריע וילדה זכר, isha ki tazria veyalda zachar, if a woman gives
forth seed and gives birth to a male, and then dot dot
dot, וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו, ubayom hashmini yimol besar orlato, and
on the eighth day you shall circumcise his flesh of the foreskin.
So it's ילדה זכר, yalda zachar, עד שיהא זכר משעת לידה, ad
sheyehe zachar mishat leida, it has to be male from the time
of birth. And therefore since that was not true here, the weight
of the eighth day that it overrides שבת Shabbat would not apply.
רב שרביא אמר, Rav Sharvia amar, רב שרביא Rav Sharvia says the
same דרשה drasha from the פסוק, pasuk, from the same דרשה drasha
from the same פסוק pasuk but with a different halachic implication: אף
אין אמו טמאה לידה. af ein imo tme'a leida. If his mother
gives birth to this child who again at that time his identity
as male or female was not noticeable, then there is no טומאת
לידה. tumat leida. She does not have any of the impurity that
comes with childbirth. If she's bleeding she would be a נידה, niddah,
but she would not have the impurity that comes with childbirth. דאמר
קרא De'amar kra because the פסוק pasuk says: אישה כי תזריע וילדה
זכר, isha ki tazria veyalda zachar, וטמאה שבעת ימים, vetame'a shivat yamim,
that comes even before the ברית מילה. brit milah. When she gives
birth to a male she's טמאה tme'a for seven days. עד שיהא
זכר משעת לידה. ad sheyehe zachar mishat leida. It has to be
noticeable as a male from the time of birth. And since this
one is neither a male at the time of birth or noticeable
as such or a female, then therefore according to this it wouldn't
fall into either פרשה parsha of the טומאה tumah of a male
child or a female child, and the mother would not be טמאה.
tme'a.
It would stay for דרבנן derabbanan I'm assuming. It probably would.
And there's a bigger חידוש chidush here. Here it's even if it
clearly was a male, it just wasn't known, it would be like
a קל וחומר kal vachomer by a case of אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, absolutely.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, right. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute: עד שיהא זכר משעת לידה. ad sheyehe
zachar mishat leida. מתיבי, Meseivei, the גמרא Gemara says, I'll challenge you
on
this: המפלת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. hamapelet tumtum ve'androgynos. There you go, if a
woman gives birth and the child is a טומטום tumtum or an
אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, it's funny that it really should be like three things
if she miscarries, excuse me, then even if you just don't sort
of
know what the child is. But it really should be
המפלת כמה hamapelet kama or היולדת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. hayoledet tumtum ve'androgynos. Let
me just check the רשב"ם Rashbam how he reads it
here.
He says המפלת טומטום. hamapelet tumtum.
Yeah, I don't know why it דוקא davka is המפלת טומטום, hamapelet
tumtum, but anyway if a woman anyway if the child is a
טומטום tumtum or an אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, so you don't know, you know,
whether it's male or female, so the הלכה halacha is, but the
same could be if it was a המפלת hamapelet and you just
weren't able to identify it, anyway, תשב לזכר ולנקבה. teshvei lezachar ulenekeiva.
So it's a doubt whether the child is male or female, so
she has to have both stringencies. What are both stringencies? A woman
who gives birth to a male child is טמאה tme'a for seven
days. And then the following thirty-three days is called דם טוהר, dam
tohar, if even if she bleeds during the next thirty-three days, she's
טהורה. tehorah. For a female, she's טמאה tame'ah for fourteen days, and
even if she bleeds into the next sixty-six days, she's טהורה. tehorah.
A child you don't know if it's male or if it's female,
you have both stringencies. So what it would be would be
fourteen days of exactly, exactly.
So if it were a male, you would have right day one
to seven she'd be טמאה tame'ah and then from basically day eight
to day forty, even if she would bleed, she would be טהורה,
tehorah, okay, even even if she bleeds. That's דם טוהר, dam tohar,
that's for a male. And for a female, it's day one to
fourteen she is טמאה, tame'ah, which I should probably be using some
different color but okay whatever, we'll use orange, it's the closest thing
to
red, okay, טמאה. tame'ah.
That looks like seventy-eight, whatever. Anyway, and then from here to day
to day eighty, okay, she's טהורה. tehorah. So this woman you don't
know whether whether it's a boy or a girl, so you treat
it like a girl and she's טמאה tame'ah for the first fourteen
days, and you treat it like a boy and the special הלכה
halacha that even if she bleeds she's טהורה tehorah is over by
day forty, okay? So that's the הלכה halacha of תשב לזכר ולנקבה.
teshev l'zachar u'l'nekeivah. But the bottom line is, is that she is
טמאה לידה, tame'ah leida, you just don't know which. There's no הלכה
halacha that because the child is unidentifiable as male or female that
somehow she's excluded from the category. Yes?
She's טהורה tehorah for her husband, right, but is she טהורה tehorah
also for like
No, she cannot eat קרבנות korbanot until the end of the forty
or the eighty days, that is correct. Okay, so the גמרא gemara
says תיובתא דרב שביא תיובתא, tiyufta d'Rav Shavya tiyufta, that the complete
contradiction of רב שביא, Rav Shavya, even if you cannot identify the
child as male or
female, nevertheless, it is not excluded from that category, and she has
to just take both stringencies. So the גמרא gemara says לימא תיהוי
תיובתא דרב שיזבי, leima teihavei tiyufta d'Rav Shizvi, let's say it's also
a contradiction to רב שיזבי, Rav Shizvi, because רב שיזבי Rav Shizvi
also made a דרשה drasha from the פסוק, pasuk, except he applied
it to the law of ברית מילה, bris milah, to say that
שבת shabbos doesn't you don't override ברית מילה bris milah on שבת
shabbos doesn't you know, ברית מילה bris milah does not override שבת.
shabbat. But once we're saying that that's not what this פסוק pasuk
means, this פסוק pasuk is not meant to exclude the case of
טומטום, tumtum, so let's say that we also reject רב שיזבי Rav
Shizvi and we would say that if a baby was born this
way and then before the eighth day it became clear he was
a male, you would do a ברית מילה bris milah on שבת.
shabbos. So the גמרא gemara so it would seem, right, if you
can't דרש darsh the פסוק pasuk one way for the טומאה, tumah,
you can't apply it the other way for the ברית מילה. bris
milah. So the גמרא gemara says no, תנא ספוקי מספקא ליה, tanna
sapokei mesapka leih, the
תנא tanna is uncertain how to read the פסוק. pasuk. Should we
make this דרשה drasha or not? Should we say that the פסוק
pasuk is excluding a child who is not identifiable as male or
female? ולחומרא, v'l'chumra, and it's going stringently, which means that when it
comes to the question of טומאה, tumah, we're going to say the
verse is not excluding such a child and we're just going to
treat him as a doubt and therefore he's going to have this
הלכה, halacha, טמאה tame'ah for fourteen days and then at the end
of forty that special status ends, because maybe the פסוק pasuk that
said, you know, וילדה זכר v'yalda zachar is not meant to exclude
a child who was a טומטום. tumtum. However, when it comes to
ברית מילה, bris milah, maybe we'll go the other way and say
maybe the פסוק pasuk is meant to exclude a child who was
a טומטום, tumtum, and therefore we can't have it override שבת shabbos
if it's possibly being excluded from this verse. So does the phrase
וילדה זכר, v'yalda zachar, right, that's the phrase, the phrase is וילדה
זכר, v'yalda zachar, and there are two הלכות halachos about this,
וילדה זכר. v'yalda zachar. So one הלכה halacha is וטמאה שבעת ימים,
v'tam'ah shivas yamim, and the other הלכה halacha is וביום
השמיני ימול. u'v'yom hashemini yimol. So is that phrase וילדה זכר v'yalda
zachar meant to exclude a טומטום? tumtum? Okay? So here we say
maybe it doesn't exclude a טומטום, tumtum, so therefore there's a ספק
safek and we're going to say she's טמאה tame'ah because maybe a
טומטום tumtum is not excluded, then it would be a doubt and
she'd be have this like stringent way about fourteen and forty, but
basically we don't know here, however, we say maybe a טומטום tumtum
is excluded and therefore we're going to say that doesn't override שבת,
shabbos, okay? We're be stringent both ways, because we don't know whether
the פסוק pasuk excludes a טומטום, tumtum, okay? So that's what the
גמרא gemara is saying. So both can be true. She's טמאה, tame'ah,
but we're still going to say it doesn't override שבת shabbos because
maybe this פסוק pasuk really does exclude a טומטום. tumtum. So now
let's see, that's very reasonable, but now let's see what the גמרא
gemara says. אי
הכי, ei hachi, says the גמרא, gemara, if that were true, that
we really don't know whether the פסוק pasuk excludes a טומטום tumtum
or not, maybe a טומטום tumtum is fully excluded, תשב לזכר ולנקבה
ולנידה מיבעי ליה, teshev l'zachar u'l'nekeivah u'l'niddah miba'ei leih, קשיא. kashya. Then
that if that were true, then even in this case of the
טומאה, tumah, maybe a טומטום tumtum would be excluded. Now, if a
טומטום tumtum was excluded, how would that add to an extra stringency?
We're already saying she's טמאה tmeiah 14 days, and her special status
is over by day 40, right? That's דם טהור. dam tohar. But
so, could there be, would there be an additional stringency if a
טומטום tumtum was excluded? Yes, because if a טומטום tumtum was excluded,
she wouldn't have any of the days of טהרה. toharah. So, if
a טומטום tumtum was excluded, then she, and let's say she had
bled, she'd be טמאה tmeiah seven days, so there would be a
leniency that it wouldn't go for 14 days, or let's say she
didn't bleed at all, but there would be a stringency that during
this, day 15 to 40, if she were to bleed, she'd be
טמאה. tmeiah. So, if it's really true that this might exclude a
טומטום, tumtum, then we have all three possibilities right now: maybe it's
a male, maybe female, maybe the category of טומאת לידה tumas leidah
doesn't apply at all. But that's a stringency because, I mean, there's
a stringency component to it, because if the category of טומאת לידה
tumas leidah doesn't apply, there's no דם טהור. dam tohar. Okay. So,
then therefore, we should have said not only is she טמאה tmeiah
like a זכר zachar and a נקבה, nekeivah, she should also be
טמאה tmeiah as a נדה, niddah, which means no special status of
דם טהור. dam tohar. Okay. So, since it doesn't say that, it
only says זכר ונקבה, zachar unekeivah, it sounds like a טומטום tumtum
is not excluded. He's definitely in the category, we just don't know
male or female. And therefore, in this case, the ברית מילה bris
milah should be on day eight, even on שבת, Shabbos, that the
פסוק pasuk does not exclude a טומטום. tumtum. That's what it sounds
like. Because if there was a possibility that that excluded a טומטום,
tumtum, again, we should have raised the possibility here that there's no
דם טהור, dam tohar, that it's all, that maybe she's a נדה.
niddah. So, that's what the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי תשב לזכר
ולנקבה ולנדה מבעיא ליה? ee hachi teshev lazachar ulin'keivah uliniddah mibaiya lei?
קשיא. kashya. All right, we don't know exactly, maybe it should have
said ולנדה, uliniddah, right? So, the גמרא Gemara sort of acknowledges that's
a bit of a problem, but nevertheless. Now, I just want to...
not enough to say תיובתא. tiyufta.
Not enough to say תיובתא. tiyufta. So, it still is possible that
we can say she has טומאת לידה, tumas leidah, and on the
other hand, we're going to be, because it's, you know, at the
other hand, maybe a טומטום tumtum is totally excluded and therefore the
ברית מילה bris milah will not be, I mean, there will be
a ברית מילה bris milah once you find out he's male, but
it doesn't have the special הלכה halacha that it overrides שבת. Shabbos.
I want to say something about this before we go on though,
because it's very interesting, because the גמרא Gemara had no problems with
the statements before, for example, that a טומטום tumtum wasn't included in
the פסוק pasuk about והיה הבן הבכור, vehaya haben habechor, that he's,
that he doesn't get a double portion. בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer
umoreh, what's the difference? If you're excluding a טומטום tumtum from those
פסוקים, psukim, why are you not excluding the טומטום, tumtum, why might
you not be excluding the טומטום tumtum from these פסוקים? psukim? And
I would like to suggest, and maybe I'm being a little anachronistic
or whatever, but it's a difference here between sex and gender. Right,
זכר zachar is male or female. בן ben is boy, boy or
girl, right? So, like, man or woman, which is more of a
gender category than a sex category. Well, it doesn't say, it doesn't
say הבן הזכר, haben hazachar, it says בן, ben, right? So, it
could be that because it's a very funny statement of the גמרא:
Gemara: עד שיהא בן משעת לידה. ad sheyehei ben mishas leidah. It
is a בן משעת לידה. ben mishas leidah, It shouldn't say עד
שיודע שהוא בן משעת לידה, ad sheyivadei shehu ben mishas leidah, right?
It doesn't say it's known that he's a boy, it actually says
it's not a boy from the moment of birth. What do you
mean, it is a boy, you just don't know it? Right? But
if you're talking about gender, which is more of a societal construct,
so if you don't know yet if the child is male or
female, so you haven't yet categorized him as a boy. Right? The
category boy as a
gender construct, right, if you... so, he's not in some way, he's
not yet a boy. He is a male or female, you're just
ignorant of it, but that's like
a fact of the genitalia and so on. It's not a... it's
of the biology, it's not a societal fact. So, I think that
it's possible to say he's not yet a בן ben because you
haven't yet identified what his sex is, so he's not a בן
ben משעת לידה, mishas leidah. but he is a זכר משעת לידה,
zachar mishas leidah, you're just not aware of it. So, that's my
nice little modern דרוש drash on that, okay, about the difference between
sex and gender. All right, so anyway, now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבא תני כוותיה דרבי אמי. amar Rava tani
k'vasi d'Rabbi Ami. We taught like Rabbi Ami. Which one was Rabbi
Ami? Oh, about that he doesn't get the בכור bechor portion if
his genitalia is not clear at the moment of birth. Here's the
ברייתא: braisa: בן, ben, it says והיה הבן הבכור לשניאה, vehaya haben
habechor linsnia, בן ולא טומטום, ben v'lo tumtum, בן ben and not
a טומטום. tumtum. If it's a טומטום, tumtum, even if it's... discovered
later, what that it's a boy, that it's nevertheless, since it was
not that way from the moment of birth, he does not get
a double portion. So it says והיה הבן הבכור vehaya haben habechor
ולא ספק, velo safek, not if it's doubtful if he's the בכור.
bechor. So בשלמא bishlama בן ולא טומטום, ben velo tumtum, I understand
the הלכה halacha of בן ולא טומטום ben velo tumtum to רב
אמי Rav Ami like רב אמי Rav Ami said, since it was
not known from the moment of birth that it was a boy,
he does not get the double portion. אלא Ela בכור ולא ספק
bechor velo safek לאפוקי מאי, lafukei mai, what's it coming to exclude?
So it should be pretty obvious, you could come up with a
scenario you don't know who's the בכור. bechor. So the גמרא Gemara
says לאפוקי מאי, lafukei mai, לאפוקי מאי דדרש רבא, lafukei mai dedarash
Rava, like רבא Rava said, דדרש רבא. dedarash Rava. שתי נשים, Shte
nashim, a man had two wives, שילדו שני זכרים sheyaldu shene zacharim
במערה, bame'ara, and they both gave birth to two boys and they
were
in a
cave, they were hiding from the non-Jews, who knows why they were
in the cave. Anyway, and at the time they gave birth everything
was dark and the moms didn't hold on to their kids and
you don't know which one gave birth to like maybe you know
which one gave birth first or which one, or maybe you know
which mother gave birth first but then you don't know which boy
is which because you got the two boys mixed up. Okay? So
you got the two boys mixed up and you don't know which
one is the firstborn. כותבין הרשאה זה לזה. kotvin harsha'a ze laze.
So רבא Rava said, okay, one of them is entitled to the
חלק בכור. chelek bechor. They don't know which one it is, right?
לאה's Leah son is entitled to the בכורה bechora portion, but each
child doesn't know is he לאה's Leah son or is he רחל's
Rachel son. So what do they do? So ראובן Reuven and יוסף,
Yosef, we'll call those the two sons, okay? They basically say, okay,
יוסף Yosef says to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן, Reuven, I am writing to
you a power of attorney in case I am the בכור, bechor,
I am giving you my power of attorney so that you can
collect my בכור bechor portion on my behalf. Okay? And then and
then ראובן Reuven goes and he says, he doesn't even have to
say the same thing, that's the funny thing, it's not really כותבין
הרשאה זה לזה, kotvin harsha'a ze laze, you don't really need to
go both ways. ראובן Reuven goes to the other brothers and he
says, I'm here to collect the double portion. I'm either collecting it
on my own behalf, either I'm the בכור, bechor, or I am
collecting it on יוסף's Yosef behalf, but either way I'm entitled to
a double portion, I'm going to collect it. Okay? And he goes
ahead and he collects it. What?
There's two others to divide everything evenly.
Fine. Right. Correct. Correct. It's correct. Okay, anyway, so that's what he
says, that's how you solve the problem. One of them is a
בכור, bechor, you don't know which one, so by giving
the power of attorney you can go ahead and you can get
it from the other brothers.
So between ראובן Reuven and יוסף Yosef they get three portions.
Right. Exactly. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא. Amar lei Rav Papa leRava.
So that was what רבא Rava said, which means that you are
fundamentally entitled, it's just a ספק. safek. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא,
Amar lei Rav Papa leRava, ושלח רבין, veshalach Rabin, but רבין Rabin
sent a message from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. דבר זה שאלתי לכל
רבותי, Davar ze sha'alti lechol rabotai, I asked this question to all
of my rabbis, ולא אמרו לי דבר, velo amru li davar, and
they didn't give me a response. ברם כך אמרו. Beram kach amru.
It's very funny. He says let's finish reading. So first of all,
it's funny he says that he didn't get a response and then
he's going to say the response that he got. They didn't give
me an answer, but here's what they said. Okay, משמיה דרבי ינאי.
mishmeia deRabbi Yannai. Maybe it means they didn't have their own answer
but here's what they relate in the name of רבי ינאי, Rabbi
Yannai, that it actually matters what the scenario was in that
case. הוכרו ולבסוף נתערבו, hukru ulevasof nitarvu, if initially each mother, like
it was known, oh, okay, this was the firstborn child, and you
knew who was the firstborn child and then afterwards the babies got
mixed up and you couldn't identify who was who. So in that
case, then the firstborn is entitled to the double portion and it's
a ספק, safek, so the way you solve it is what you
said. כותבין הרשאה זה לזה, kotvin harsha'a ze laze, you just write
a power of attorney. לא הוכרו, Lo hukru, but let's say it
was never identified. As soon as they were born, they were mixed
up and nobody ever said, oh, that's my son. It was never
known which was the firstborn son, not even for one minute. Okay?
In that case, אין כותבין הרשאה זה לזה. ein kotvin harsha'a ze
laze. They cannot write a power of attorney. And this is the
דרשה drasha of בכור ולא ספק. bechor velo safek. So it doesn't
mean to exclude every any case of a doubt. It means it's
similar to the idea ולא טומטום. velo tumtum. If from the very
moment of birth it was never known, there was not even one
minute after birth that it was known that this is the בכור,
bechor, then he loses his status of בכור. bechor. Okay?
So that's the דרשה drasha of בכור ולא ספק, bechor velo safek,
when it was never known. הדר אוקי רבא אמורא עליה. Hadar oki
Rava amora alei. Then רבא Rava put up an אמורא. amora. אמורא
Amora we know like the same, it's there's a double use of
the word אמורא amora the same way there's a double use of
the word תנא. tanna. תנא Tanna we often use to refer to
the rabbis who are the authorities of the משנה, Mishna, but sometimes
the תנא, tanna, I sometimes call it a big T Tanna and
a small t tanna. Sometimes the תנא tanna is the person who
repeats the words of the תנאים. Tannaim. He memorizes them and repeats
them. So the אמורא amora is either the all of the rabbis
of the גמרא, Gemara, or they are the loudspeaker of the rabbi.
He goes up to make a דרשה drasha in public, he says
it to this guy who's called his אמורא, amora, and this person
then belts it out to the whole crowd. Okay. So אוקי רבא
אמורא ליה, Uki Rava Amora lei, so רבא Rava put a stood
an אמורא Amora in front of him, and דרש darash and explicated
to the masses the following thing. דברים שאמרתי לכם טעות הן בידי.
Devarim she-amarti lachem ta'ut hen beyadi. That thing that I told you
before the other day, I was wrong, I made a mistake. Okay,
it's not true. They can't always write a הרשאה. harsha'a. It depends
on the case. ברם
כך אמרו משום רבי ינאי, Beram kach amru mishum Rabi Yannai, here's
what it is said in the name of רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai.
הוקרו לבסוף נתערבו, Hukru levasof nitarvu, if the בכור bechor or was
originally identified and then it got confused and you didn't know who
was who, כותבין הרשאה זה לזה. kotvin harsha'a zeh la-zeh. Then he's
entitled to the בכור bechor portion of the בכור bechor and you
don't know, so you write a power of attorney. לא הוקרו, Lo
hukru, but if it was never identified even for one minute who
the בכור bechor was, אין כותבין הרשאה זה לזה. ein kotvin harsha'a
zeh la-zeh. They cannot write it one to another. Now one would
imagine, you could also imagine a case sort of similar to the
טומטום, tumtum, which is that it was not recognized at the first
moment but it was somehow recognized later. You know, I don't know,
let's say you did DNA testing or something like that, right, right?
So I would imagine it would be the same as the טומטום
tumtum case. It doesn't matter even if it's identified later, it has
to have been identified at that first moment. And otherwise the child
does not have a status of a בכור. bechor.
Yeah, but don't we also say נאמן אדם לומר זה בני בכורי?
Ne'eman adam lomar zeh beni bechori? Yes, right? So let's say he
comes, it wasn't known, like he has some wife in מדינת הים.
Medinat ha-yam. Right, then he comes out.
I mean then it wasn't known to us in this town but
it was known to people. Now I think it's an interesting question
about let's say it was not known to anybody other than the
man himself, right? The people in this other town, I don't know,
right? You know, he was out in a forest with his wife,
nobody knew. I think as long as it was known to somebody,
known to the mother, known to the man, it is a good
question to whom does it have to be known. But it does
not have to be known to everybody, to the people in the
town.
But if the father and we have the scenario, I mean who's
believed? Like the father says my בכור bechor and the mother says
this is my בכור. bechor. Like do we go by the mother
then?
No, it's a special belief, we're going to get to it, it's
coming up, but there's a special understanding that a trust that the
Torah gave or נאמנות, ne'emanut, like you know, a special weight that
the Torah gave to the father's testimony about this.
Okay, so even if the mother says, you know, I really was
with another man. Right.
Oh, that's an interesting point. It doesn't matter, so what if she
was with another man? Oh, you mean she says it's not his
kid? Yeah, ממזר. mamzer. No, you wouldn't believe the mother. If she
says she gave birth before it wouldn't matter, it could still be
the father's firstborn. No,
yeah, I mean, you know, if you had real evidence, but otherwise
no, the Torah doesn't, it all gives special נאמנות ne'emanut to the
father's testimony, but we're getting up to that, we haven't seen that
yet.
So you're saying even in the face of contradictory testimony from the
mother?
That would be correct. Yeah, we're going to see, it's going to
come up right, pretty much a case like that's going to come
up, not exactly, but okay.
Okay, now שלחו ליה בני אקרא דאגמא, Shalchu lei benei Akra De-Agma,
the people of this I don't know אקרא דאגמא, Akra De-Agma, the
swamp of אקרא Akra or something. לשמואל, Le-Shmuel, anyway, I don't know
what an אקרא Akra whatever.
It must be a well-known tourist spot.
Yeah, exactly. They sent, they sent the following message to שמואל. Shmuel.
ילמדנו רבנו, Yelamdenu rabenu, let our master teach us. היו מוחזקין בזה
שהוא בכור. Hayu muchzakin be-zeh she-hu bechor.
Okay, there you go Michael, you see you anticipated the גמרא. Gemara.
Everybody assumed that a certain person was the בכור. bechor. ואמר אביו
על אחר בכור, Ve-amar aviv al acher bechor, and the father said,
no, this other kid is the בכור. bechor. Okay, so that nobody
ever knew about this other kid. He said, yeah, I had this
other boy, I had him on מדינת הים Medinat ha-yam or whatever,
he's the בכור bechor and so on. So מהו, mahu,
what's the הלכה? halacha? שלחו להו, Shalchu le-hu, כותבין הרשאה זה לזה.
kotvin harsha'a zeh la-zeh. So he's כותבין הרשאה kotvin harsha'a
writes זה לזה. zeh la-zeh. He treated it like the other case,
it's a ספק. safek. The חזקה chazaka establishes one kid as a
בכור, bechor, the father's testimony establishes the other kid as a בכור.
bechor. So it's not a problem that it was not הוכר, hukar,
it was הוכר, hukar, we just don't know right now, because now
we have contradictory evidence. Right? At the moment of birth we'll assume
it was known. So therefore it's a ספק, safek, so they solve
it by writing a הרשאה. harsha'a. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, it's not a ספק. safek. Okay, yes, you have contradictory things.
On the one hand you have a חזקה, chazaka, on the other
hand you have the father's testimony. But just ממה נפשך, man nafshach,
make up your mind, which one of those is going to have
more weight in determining the facts? And that actually is a debate
of תנאים Tannaim that we're going to see. ממה נפשך, Man nafshach,
make up your mind. אי כרבנן סבירא ליה, Ei ke-Rabanan sevira lei,
if you hold like the רבנן, Rabanan, לשלחו כרבנן, lishlachu ke-Rabanan, send
like the רבנן. Rabanan. The רבנן Rabanan say
that you go by the חזקה chazaka and not by the father's,
if the father's testimony works if there's no presumption of fact. But
if there's already a חזקה chazaka that a certain person is the
בכור, bechor, the father's testimony does not work against it. So then
just rule that way and say that you go by the guy
who was presumed to be the בכור. bechor. אי כרבי יהודה סבירא
ליה, Ei ke-Rabbi Yehuda sevira lei, if you hold like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that you always go by the father's testimony even against
a חזקה, chazaka, לשלחו כרבי יהודה, lishlachu ke-Rabbi Yehuda, just rule like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and say go by the father's testimony. So
what do you mean that it's a doubt? So the answer is
obvious. The גמרא Gemara says מסתפקא ליה, mistapka lei, שמואל Shmuel has
a doubt how to rule. אי כרבי יהודה, אי כרבנן. Ei ke-Rabbi
Yehuda, ei ke-Rabanan. He doesn't know. but do you go by רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who goes by the father's testimony, or by the
רבנן Rabbanan who go by the חזקה? chazaka? So since he doesn't
know, according to either one of those it's clear who the בכור
Bechor is. But שמואל Shmuel doesn't know which way to פסקן, pasken,
so therefore שמואל Shmuel says it's a doubt what the הלכה Halacha
is, so you write a הרשאה. harsha. We have something similar to
that talking about personal status like nowadays in cases for example about
surrogate motherhood, right? It's still a raging debate who do you consider
to be the mother: the woman who donated the egg or the
woman who carried the baby. So you could say the child definitely
has one of them as the mother, you just don't know which
one, right? So הלכה, halacha, if you're a פוסק, posek, you might
not know who to פסקן pasken like. I can't decide between this
פסק psak and that פסק. psak. So if, say, if one of
those mothers was not Jewish, you'll say, well, like, just do a
גירות מספק. geirus misafek. Now some פוסקים poskim say no, definitely it's
a non-Jew, you go by the birth mother. And others will say
no, definitely by the mother who carried him, definitely he's a Jew,
you go by the mother who donated the egg, or the reverse
depending on the case. So if you go by certain פוסקים poskim
the answer is definite. But another פוסק posek might say, well, I
can't decide between those two. So play it safe, just do a
גירות מספק, geirus misafek, which is often what פוסקים poskim say. So
here too שמואל Shmuel says according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the
answer is obvious, according to the רבנן Rabbanan the answer is obvious.
I just don't know which one to פסקן pasken like, so write
a הרשאה. harsha. And that's how you'll solve it. Okay. דתניא. D'tanya.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי כרבי יהודה אי כרבנן,
ei k'Rabbi Yehuda ei k'Rabbanan, מאי היא? mai hi? What is this
debate? דתניא, D'tanya, we turn to a ברייתא, Baraisa, יכיר, yakkir, כי
את הבכור בן השנואה יכיר. ki et habechor ben hasenua yakkir. He
must recognize
the בכור Bechor of the hated wife. That's the פסוק pasuk in
the תורה. Torah. So it means that the father's recognizing who the
בכור bechor is is of halachic weight. Okay, so יכירנו לאחרים, Yakkirenu
leacharim, he must acknowledge him or make him known to others. מכאן
אמר רבי יהודה, mikan amar Rabbi Yehuda, נאמן אדם לומר זה בני
בכור. ne'eman adam lomar zeh bni bechor. A person is believed to
say this is my firstborn son, and that has special halachic weight
more than a normal one individual, one person's testimony. That the תורה
Torah gives it
as special weight.
וכשם שנאמן אדם לומר זה בני בכור, ukshem shene'eman adam lomar zeh
bni bechor, in the same way a person is believed to say
this is my firstborn son, כך נאמן אדם לומר זה בן גרושה
וזה בן חלוצה. kach ne'eman adam lomar zeh ben gerusha v'zeh ben
chalutza. He could say about a son of his, if he's a
כהן, Kohen, that actually his mother was a גרושה, gerusha, a divorcee,
or a חלוצה, chalutza, a woman who underwent חליצה chalitza by יבום,
yibum, and therefore nobody knew it, but I'm telling you the woman
I married was a divorcee, and therefore this child of mine is
not really a כהן, Kohen, he's a חלל. chalal. Now how do
you make that jump from an issue of דיני ממונות dinei mamonus
of getting a portion of an estate to affecting somebody's personal status
as a כהן Kohen is a big question. But hold on, so
we'll get back to that in a minute, but first let's just
hear what the רבנן's Rabbanan position is. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, but
the sages say, אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman, he's not believed. Now does
that really mean the sages say the father's not believed ever to
claim who his firstborn son is? So אמר ליה רב נחמן בר
יצחק לרבא, amar leh Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak l'Rava, בשלמא לרבי יהודה
היינו דכתיב יכיר, bishlama l'Rabbi Yehuda haynu dechtiv yakkir, for רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that the father is believed, I understand why the תורה
Torah says יכיר. yakkir. אלא לרבנן יכיר למה לי? ela l'Rabbanan yakkir
lama li? What's the force of the word יכיר yakkir for the
rabbis? בצריך הכרה, betzarich hikkira, so if the child needs to be
recognized, meaning if nobody knows who the בכור bechor is, the father
is believed, and that was some cases we had at the end
of the day yesterday. So everybody agrees the father is believed to
say who the בכור bechor is when there's general doubt. The question
is, is the father believed to say who the בכור bechor is
against a general perception that somebody else is the בכור, bechor, against
a חזקה? chazaka? Okay, that's the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and the חכמים Chachamim and that was the case that was presented
to שמואל. Shmuel. There was a חזקה chazaka that one kid was
a בכור, bechor, the father identified another
kid. There רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even there the father is
believed to say who the בכור bechor is. אלא חכמים ela Chachamim
say no, if there's a presumption and a חזקה, chazaka, he is
not believed against that.
Yeah, but I'm saying why? Meaning like, if this isn't like fact.
You know, there is חזקה, chazaka, fact, and
if someone saw it, it's not a חזקה, chazaka, then it's known,
there's no question. Right. But if there's just a חזקה, chazaka, I
mean, it's like who knows? I don't know, I don't know, I
don't know. That's what the rumor says, right? That's what you mean.
Well no, there's, and
the father's saying I have definite information. The rumor is not definite
information at all.
I understand, but I understand. First of all, a חזקה chazaka is
not just, there's a gap between like, I don't know, it's just
a rumor to saying that there's a חזקה. chazaka. Like we saw
before, a חזקה chazaka is everywhere he goes, everybody calls him oh
he's the head of the family, oh he's whatever, he's generally, you
know, treated and assumed to be in the community as the בכור.
bechor. It's not just a question of rumor. Okay? It's not hearsay.
That's very different than a חזקה. chazaka. Okay? חזקה chazaka is that
that is the way he is accepted within society and treated within
society. Now it is true the father has special information, but he's
still an עד אחד. ed echad. And if somebody came and, you
know, I don't know, there was a עד אחד ed echad and
he was a doctor and he says I was the doctor and
I was there when he was born or whatever, although I don't
know, you don't know what the father was doing somewhere else, you
know, whatever, but anyway it would just be עד אחד. ed echad.
עד אחד ed echad against חזקה chazaka generally doesn't work.
How does חזקה chazaka get there? Meaning
like...
So okay, but the father is not two עדים. edim. So that's
the question: what is the weight of the father's testimony? Okay, the
חזקה chazakah isn't hearsay, the חזקה chazakah is based on a lot
of circumstantial and ongoing evidence about how this person is seen in
the community and in society and by his family, okay, and that
creates the חזקה. chazakah. And then the question is what weight do
you need to override that? So one person's testimony might not be
enough, or normally it wouldn't be enough unless the תורה Torah gave
it special weight. So that's the question: how much special weight did
the תורה Torah give the father's testimony? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says now, אלא אמר רב אמי וצריכא הכא. Ela amar Rav Ami
vetzaricha hacha. למאי הלכתא? lemai hilcheta? So when do you need to
give belief according to the רבנן? rabbanan? In what cases do you
believe the father?
רש"י Rashi says הכא בכל בנים. hacha bechol banim.
I am going to, I am going to finish and then you'll
ask your question. Okay? So, so the גמרא Gemara says, וצריכא הכא.
vetzaricha hacha. So the גמרא Gemara says, למאי הלכתא? lemai hilcheta? One
minute. So according to the רבנן, rabbanan, the father is believed in
a case when there's no חזקה chazakah to say "this is my
בכור." bechor. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. If there's no
חזקה chazakah that this is—and the father's believed to say this son
is my בכור, bechor, why does he need special believability? He could,
he could accomplish that even if he wasn't believed. How could he
accomplish that? So the גמרא Gemara says, למיתב לו פי שנים. lemetiv
lo pi shenayim. So the relevance of identifying this kid as the
בכור bechor when there's no חזקה chazakah is that he'll get double.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לא יהא אלא אחר. lo yehei ela
acher.
So even if the son was some stranger, אילו בעי למיתב לו
במתנה מי לא יהיב ליה? ilu bei lemetiv lo bematanah mi lo
yahiv lei? So he could have just given him this extra portion
as a gift. So here the father is—and the father's saying, "This
kid is my בכור." bechor. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, why
do we need the תורה Torah to tell me he's believed? He
should be believed based on that basic principle known as מיגו. migo.
Since if I wanted this kid, who is, you know, maybe you're
doubting he's the בכור, bechor, if I wanted him to get that
extra portion, I could have given it to him anyway. I could
have just gifted it to him. So since I would have been
able to have him get that double portion by gifting it to
him, I should be believed when I say that he's the בכור.
bechor. So why do you need the תורה Torah to believe me
to say he's the בכור bechor since I should be believed on
the principle of מיגו? migo? You understand the point? The whole relevance
of being a בכור bechor is that he gets an extra portion.
Well, I could just give it to him anyway right now. So
therefore believe me anyway based on מיגו. migo. Why do you need
the special fact that the תורה Torah believed me? So the גמרא
Gemara says, לא, צריכא בנכסים שנפלו לו לאחר מכאן. lo, tzericha binechasim
shenafelu lo le'achar mikan. After, right now I'm saying he's the בכור.
bechor. Okay, it's true, right now even without the special sort of
weight the תורה Torah gave my testimony, that would be believed that
he would get a double portion based on the property I have
now because I could have given him that portion right now. But
let's say after I make that statement I win the lottery, okay?
So my מיגו migo doesn't work for all those extra money I
gave the lottery. In order for him to get now a double
portion in that, I have to once again say he's a בכור,
bechor, right? When I say right now, I say right now he's
a בכור. bechor. If the תורה Torah didn't believe me, the only
reason you would believe that statement was because if—let's say right now
I have a hundred thousand dollars to my name, okay? And I've
got, what do I have? Four kids, or, or three kids. So
if I'm saying he's a בכור, bechor, I'm saying he's going to
get an extra two hundred fifty thousand and the other seven hundred
fifty will be divided amongst three kids, right? Okay, so I would
say like, "Look, believe me when I say he's a בכור bechor
because even if he weren't a בכור bechor I could give him
two hundred fifty thousand dollars right now." So therefore when I say
he's a בכור, bechor, you should believe me. Fine, we'll believe you
to the extent that you could have accomplished that end goal and
given him two hundred fifty thousand dollars. So your statement that he
has a בכור bechor is believed to award him two hundred fifty
thousand dollars because that's what you were prepared to give him right
now. Okay, now I win a hundred million dollars, okay? So, and
then I, or whoever, ראובן Reuven let's say, wins a hundred million
dollars then he drops dead a minute later. Okay? So the kid
doesn't get an extra portion in that hundred million. Why? You already
told him, you already said he's the בכור. bechor. But that was
only believed with the weight of what he could have done at
that moment. If there was no special belief that the תורה Torah
gave him, the weight of that statement only had weight because of
the מיגו, migo, of what the father could have done anyway.
But the father couldn't anyway have given, have given at that moment
when he said it, two weeks ago, he could not have given
him, you know—right,
but when he won the lottery he could have done it.
But he didn't say then he's a בכור. bechor.
But he didn't have to because he said it before.
No, that statement only has weight in court by the force of
the מיגו, migo, by the force of what he could have accomplished
even had it not been believed. That was the weight it received
in court. Why does it get weight more than it could have
had at that time? Okay, that's the principle of מיגו. migo. The
only weight it has was the weight of what he could have
done at the moment it was said.
You're saying he didn't have enough time to then say "this is
my בכור" bechor and give it to him?
Yeah, saying "this is my son בכור," bechor, if the תורה Torah
doesn't believe you, then you'll have to constantly be repeating "he's my
בכור, bechor, he's my בכור" bechor every time you earn more and
more money, or you'll have to wait till the minute before you
die to say "he's my בכור" bechor and then you might be
dead and have not got a chance to say it.
And I can't say "I hereby declare him a בכור bechor for
anything I get from now on forever"?
No, because you don't
have— Except that the fact that the תורה Torah believes you. Because
the תורה Torah believes you that he's the בכור, bechor, once you
say it, it's believed going forward. But if your statement only had
weight because of your מיגו, migo, because of what you could have
gifted, then the only weight it has is what you could have
gifted at the moment you made the statement. Okay, and that's why
the תורה Torah had to believe the father that it's a בכור,
bechor, because otherwise, that statement would have had no power on property
the father would have gotten after the fact. So now the גמרא
Gemara says one minute. The גמרא Gemara says ולרבי מאיר דאמר אדם
מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, u'l'Rav Meir de'amar adam makneh davar she'lo
ba l'olam, the גמרא Gemara says יכיר למה לי? yachir lamma li?
Ah, but according to רבי מאיר, Rav Meir, רבי מאיר Rav Meir
says you can gift something in the future. So since right now
I could say I am gifting to this kid, right, you know,
20% or whatever of all the property I'll get, I have now
and I'll get later, so that's effectively the same as saying I'm,
you know, then it would, that would work. So when I say
he's a בכור, bechor, I don't need the תורה Torah to believe
me because I could achieve the same thing even for property I'll
get in the future.
That doesn't apply to everything.
Okay, so that's obviously so. רבי מאיר Rav Meir doesn't work for
all things. So the גמרא Gemara could have answered that, but instead
the גמרא Gemara gives a different answer. The גמרא Gemara says בנכסים
שנפלו כשהוא גוסס. binchasim she'naflu k'shehu goses. That I, the person, can
only be מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam
if when it comes to the world the person's in a position
to be able to actually gift it as well. But if somebody
basically says I'm transferring to you, you know, whatever, 20% of all
the property I own now and I will get in the future,
and then when he gets it in the future he is on
his deathbed throes and he's not of sound mind to be able
to transfer it, then it doesn't work. Even for רבי מאיר Rav
Meir when you can give something that you'll get later, it's only
if when you get it later you are able to give, you
are in a position to actually give it at that time as
well. If when you get it later you are not of sound
mind and you are not in a position to give it at
then, then your gift from earlier did not work. So the bottom
line about all of this is that even if the תורה Torah
had not believed the father to say this is my son the
בכור, bechor, he would be believed up to the extent that he
could have gifted him those items, you know, he could have gifted
him that at the moment of making the statement. But that statement
would not have been helpful for property he would have had later.
And therefore the תורה Torah have to believe the father that it's
a בכור, bechor, and then that works for any property he gets
at a later time.
Yeah, back to my rumor thing. I mean, I'm just looking at
the רשב״ם Rashbam on the bottom of כ״ז עמוד א׳. Kaf Zain
Amud Aleph. It says דבעי עידין שיעידון כההוא לעד קודם דאחיו,
d'ba'ei eidim she'me'idun ke'hahu l'ad
kodem de'achav, not עידין, eidim, דכן נאמן הימנו, de'ken amen abnimani, when
do you believe them? אלא בכולה עלמא, ella be'chola alma, כיון דאמרו
לעלמא, keivan de'amaru l'alma, it says הכל, hakol, it sounds like a
rumor. Yeah,
but that's not סתם.
stam. There's different types of rumor. I mean, you're right, that word
is funny, but he refers to the earlier גמרא, Gemara, דהוו קרו
ליה בכרא, d'havu karlei bechra,
which is exactly as I described it. A rumor is oh, did
you hear somebody was a first born blah blah blah. That's not
a חזקה. chazakah. A חזקה chazakah is an impression that is created
through the way society and whatever the person has behaved and society
behaves regarding this person. Now let me go to the other point
of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so there you have, so what we
have there is for the חכמים Chachamim the תורה Torah believes the
father that it's the בכור, bechor, and the reason you need to
believe the father even though the father could gift his property is
because relating to property the father doesn't have at that time. Okay,
so the תורה Torah believes the father that this is the בכור,
bechor, but that's when it's not going against already presumptions and established
fact. If it is going against presumptions of what the reality are,
so the חכמים Chachamim say that he's not believed, and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says even there he's believed. Now, so that's one question,
to what degree is the father believed to say that this is
my son the בכור, bechor, is it against a חזקה chazakah or
not? But another interesting point is that the גמרא Gemara said that
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the father is believed to say
that my son is a בן גרושה ben grushah or בן חלוצה.
ben chalutzah. Why is it? Just because you're believed in monetary matters,
why are you believed to say that your son actually has a
פסול passul status? So תוספות Tosafot has a very interesting answer to
this question. He says, because he says imagine, Michael you'll appreciate this,
it's similar to your question. He says imagine that he says the
father says, here's a father, he's got like this 20-year-old kid, okay,
and then he says about his new baby boy who's one month
old, this is my בכור. bechor. So the תורה Torah believes him
that the baby boy is his בכור bechor and gets a double
portion. But what does he say, what must be the case there
for about the 20-year-old kid who was born to his wife 20
years ago? How could the only way that can't be the man's
בכור? bechor?
You know it's his wife, we know it's his wife. Before a
world of adoption, what was the other possibility? Adultery? Adultery. So he
says if the תורה Torah is going to believe you that this
is your בכור, bechor, then what does that mean about this 20-year-old
kid who was born to your wife 20 years ago? You're saying
he's a ממזר. mamzer. So therefore, oh. So you see implicit in
the תורה Torah believing you who is a בכור, bechor, that it
will also believe you that this kid is a ממזר. mamzer. So
therefore it must be that you're believed even on, at least according
to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that you're believed against already established fact
or already perceived fact, that you're even believed relating to personal status.
Now that's quite harsh. Now it goes that not only are we
going to believe that the guy kid isn't a כהן, kohen, we're
going to believe that he's ממש mamish a ממזר. mamzer. Okay, so
that's one way תוספות Tosfos says we can jump from the idea
of בכור bechor to the idea of personal status, that by identifying
a certain kid as a בכור bechor you might be implicitly making
a statement about the older kid. All right, is that sort of
clear? What? Yes.
Doesn't it have to be the firstborn child out of the womb
though of that woman?
No, that's only for בכור bechor for כהן, kohen, but בכור bechor
for the double portion is about the first child of the man.
Okay, so that's one דרש. drash.
Okay, did the רבנן Rabbanan dispute this and say that you wouldn't
be?
Yes, not at all clear the Rabbis agree, especially according to the
way תוספות Tosfos understands it, because that's only is if you believe
him against what's already a חזקה. chazakah. According to the רבנן, Rabbanan,
you only believe him in a completely neutral case. So they would
not necessarily be this. Okay. Anyway תוספות Tosfos has another thing that
maybe it's just like,
just sort of like an analogy. Well we're just going to assume
if the תורה Torah believes him about his son about one thing,
it'll believe him about his son about another thing, about an issue
of personal status. But this other answer is more ingenious. Okay.
So that is about the father being believed about the status of
his son. Number one, against, does it work even against a presumption
of society? And number two is, does it even work even about
a personal status and not just about a question about בכור bechor
and getting a double portion. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues
in this vein. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: היו מוחזקין בו שהוא בכור,
hayu muchzakin bo shehu bechor, ואמר אביו על אחר שהוא בכור, ve'amar
aviv al acher shehu bechor, נאמן. ne'eman. Okay, so that sounds like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. People assumed that somebody was a בכור bechor
and the father said, "No, this other kid is the בכור," bechor,
the father's believed even against
the
חזקה. chazakah. היו מוחזקין בו שאינו בכור, hayu muchzakin bo she'eino bechor,
ואמר אביו בכור הוא, ve'amar aviv bechor hu, אינו נאמן. eino ne'eman.
He's not believed. So like make up your mind, is the father
believed against the חזקה chazakah or not believed against the חזקה? chazakah?
So the גמרא Gemara says: רישא רבי יהודה וסיפא רבנן. reisha Rabbi
Yehuda vesiepa Rabbanan. Fine, this ברייתא Braitah is not one opinion. The
first part of the ברייתא Braitah says the father's believed against the
חזקה chazakah is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The second part that says
the father is not believed against the חזקה chazakah is the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Now I want to say that there's possibly another way to
read it. It could be that even the רבנן Rabbanan only say
he's not believed against the חזקה chazakah when you're effectively stealing, you
know, the בכור bechor from a certain person. People saw ראובן Reuven
was a בכור bechor and the father says, "No, שמעון Shimon is
a בכור," bechor, so the רבנן Rabbanan say we don't believe him.
But let's say there was no other brother around that we assumed
was the בכור. bechor. We just for some reason, this was your
kid, but somehow we always thought there was some older brother somewhere.
We don't know who. We just somehow were in the impression that
this was a kid you had later in life. We assumed, you
know, eh, probably he's got some older brother somewhere. But it's not
like we assumed a particular person was the בכור. bechor. So maybe
you could say that's different. I could be believed to change this
kid's status if I'm not taking the בכור bechor away from a
person who's already been identified, right? So that is the difference. In
the first case you assumed X was a בכור bechor and you
said that he's, X is not, it's Y. We don't believe him
against the חזקה. chazakah. In the other case you just assumed Y
was not. It didn't say you assumed somebody else was. And therefore
it says we do believe the father. So I have a way
that I think you could read this even according to the חכמים,
Chachamim, that the גמרא Gemara actually says that the two halves of
the ברייתא Braitah are the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: אמר בני הוא, amar beni hu,
וחזר ואמר עבדי הוא, vechazar ve'amar avdi hu, אינו נאמן. eino ne'eman.
If a person says, comes into town with a, you know, young
man with him and he says, "Yeah, this is my son," and
then later he says, "No, really he's my servant," so he's not
believed to say he's my servant because if he were your servant
you never would have called him your son. Now we have to
pause here for a moment because I did not get a chance
to explore this further, but it sounds like if he did not
start and the next thing is going to be also clear, that
if he did not start by saying, "This is my son," and
he just started by saying, "This is my servant," he would be
believed. But like I don't get it. Like I walk into town
with a young man and I say, "This is my servant." Not
my servant actually, I'm already toning it down, my slave. I say,
"This is my slave," I'm believed? Like maybe this person is a
total, like anybody ever see the movie 12 Years a Slave? Right?
You know, how do you know this person isn't a total free
man? Maybe I just hired him in the previous town as an
attendant, and now I walk into this town and I say, "He's
not an attendant, he's my slave."
Does it make a difference what the other person is saying?
Well first of all, what is the other person saying? But that's
true even in this story. Is the other person saying, "I'm a
son or a slave"? But the fact is that there seems to
be an assumption here that I'm believed to say he's my slave.
Like I'd like to know why that is. You know. So, I
don't understand how I'm believed to say about another human being that
he's my slave. Anyway, I don't, that's a pretty big question. I
don't know the answer, I'd have to look into that more. But
here it sounds like maybe I would be believed to say he's
my slave. But if I started by saying he's my son, I'm
not. Because I wouldn't say about my slave that he's my son.
עבדי הוא וחזר ואמר בני הוא, Avdi hu ve'chazar ve'amar beni hu,
if I start by saying he's my slave and then I say
he's my son, נאמן, ne'eman, then I'm believed by my second statement
that he's my son.
How did that override the previous son?
Well, that's what I meant, דמשמש לי כעבדא קאמינא, de'meshamesh li ke'avda
kamina,
no, because when I said he was my slave, I meant he,
he's such a good son, he attends to me just like a
slave. Okay, so therefore, meaning, it would be possible you would call
your son your slave. Okay, or possible your son would say, "Who
am I, your slave?" Okay,
if you ever have teenage kids, you know about that. Anyway, okay,
but it's not possible you would call your slave your, your son.
וחלופיה בבית המכס, Ve'chillufeha beveit hamachas, the opposite would be true if
you're going to at the, what do you call it, the tax
house, the, the import house. So you, so you would have to
pay taxes on, if, on your slaves. You don't have to pay
tax on your son. Okay. So your slave is part of your
property. So if you say he's my son when you were, were
meeting the tax collector and then you say, oh, he's really my
slave, you're believed, because, because you would have, because you would have
said he's your son to get out of taxes, but the reverse,
you're not believed.
Getting that extra deductions for kids.
There you go. Not deductions, you just don't have to pay taxes
on your kids. Okay. היה עובר על בית המכס ואמר בני הוא
וחזר ואמר עבדי הוא נאמן Haya over al beit hamachas ve'amar beni
hu ve'chazar ve'amar avdi hu ne'eman because there's a reason you would
have lied. Okay, אמר עבדי הוא וחזר ואמר בני הוא אינו נאמן.
Amar avdi hu ve'chazar ve'amar beni hu eino ne'eman. You obviously you're
not, why would you have said he's your slave if he weren't
your slave?
מיתיבי, Meitivei, now ask on this. היה משמשו כבן, Haya meshamesho keven,
the,
this young man was attending to you like a son would, meaning
not in a completely servile way.
ובא ואמר בני הוא וחזר ואמר עבדי הוא אינו נאמן. U'va ve'amar
beni hu ve'chazar ve'amar avdi hu eino ne'eman. You're not believed. Okay,
that's similar to what we said before.
Does it- if he was a קטן katan or גדול gadol makes
no difference?
Doesn't make a difference. That's similar to what we said before.
היה משמשו כעבד ובא ואמר עבדי הוא וחזר ואמר בני הוא אינו
נאמן, Haya meshamesho ke'eved u'va ve'amar avdi hu ve'chazar ve'amar beni hu
eino ne'eman, he's
not believed. Now that's not like we said before. We said if
you said son at the end, you are believed, that what you
meant initially when you said slave is, is he attends to me
like a slave, which is what he was doing, okay, but you
would still be believed at the end when you said he's my
son. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק התם דקרו ליה עבדא דמיצר מאה,
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hatam dekaru lei avda dematzar me'ah, no,
no, no, there when you first said he's your slave and then
your son, you're not believed. That's when you said, "This is a
slave that, that's worth a hundred," okay, דמיצר מאה. matzar me'ah. What
does that mean?
דמיצר עבדא מאה זוזי. Matzar avda me'ah zuzei. I don't know exactly
where the דמיצר, matzar, bounds? He, he's bound, he's bounded like his,
his boundaries are, how does they translate the word דמיצר matzar there?
Yeah, whatever. Anyway, it means that people are willing to pay up
to a hundred dollars for him.
You mean like he's as good as a hundred other slaves?
No, מאה זוזי. me'ah zuzei.
Anyway, you're saying that? I'm sorry.
Yeah, that's, so we're saying,
you're saying he's worth a hundred זוזי zuzei or he's saying he's
worth a hundred?
No, מאה זוזי. me'ah zuzei. Okay, so anyway, so the point is
that when you say slave and then son, you would be believed
to say son, except if you had slave and you attached a
dollar value to it. Oh, this is my slave, he's good, he's
worth a good hundred dollars. In that type of a case, you
would not actually completely, like, you know, turn him into property and
commodify him if he weren't really a slave. And then you're not
believed afterwards to say he's your son. But if you just say
slave and then son, you could say slave meant that that's how
he serves me, okay, but you didn't mean it literally. Again, what
bothers me most about all of this is that you're believed to
say that somebody is your slave. Like, you know, what is the
context, you know, or what does the other guy say? All right.
שלח ליה רב אבא לרב יוסף בר חמא, Shelach lei Rav Abba
le'Rav Yosef bar Chama, Rav Abba sent to Rav Yosef bar Chama.
האומר לחבירו עבדי גנבת והוא אומר לא גנבתי, Ha'omer lachaveiro avdi ganevta
vehu omer lo ganevti, if some, you say, "Michael, you stole my
slave," and Michael says, "No, I didn't." מה טיבו אצלך, Ma tivo
etzlecha, so what's he doing by you? So you, Michael says, אתה
מכרתו לי אתה נתתו לי במתנה, Ata mecharto li ata netato li
bematana, you sold him to me, you gave him to me as
a gift. Now, you might remember that because slaves are self-mobile, you
know, move themselves, the idea that we say that if a person's
holding onto something, חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו, Chazaka
ma shetachas yad adam harei hu shelo,
does not apply to slaves because the fact that he's in Michael's
yard doesn't mean that Michael's, that, Michael's not really possessing him in
the same way that his holding onto him proves it's his, the
slave might have taken a walk over to Michael's yard. So the
case has to be here either one of two cases where Michael's
holding him is a presumption of ownership. Either the slave is a
baby and can't walk and he's in his, and he's in his
like, you know, his bassinet or something, or the slave has been
spending three years at Michael's house. We go back to that old
stuff we did about three years being חזקה, chazaka, by, three years
of slave. Okay, so it's a case where him being in Michael's
house is a presumption that it belongs. belongs to Michael and I'm
still claiming that Michael's lying. So Michael says, no, listen, he's mine,
I would be believed, but I'll tell you what though, you know
just to make you happy, צא Tze if you want, you're so
insistent that he's yours, שבע וטול, Sheva v'tol, go ahead, take an
oath if you're willing to swear that he's your slave, you can
go ahead and swear and take him. ונשבע, V'nishba, so I go
ahead and I take an oath. אינו יכול לחזור בו, Eino yachol
lachzor bo, Michael can't say, wait, I can't, he's mine, I thought
you weren't going to take me up on it. No, once I've
taken the oath, you made that commitment, now I get to take
him back.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, that
was a closing question like אסמכתא asmachta or, you know. Yeah, okay.
So מה קמשמע לן, ma kamashmalan, now let's take a look. Why
is that a חידוש? chidush? תנינא, tanina, we've already learned that if
you are willing to like re-you know, change the parameters of a
court case and say if you do this and this because it's
not just סתם stam a deal, if it's within a בית דין
beit din context, שבועה shvuah sometimes is effective. Here it wouldn't be
effective, but if you're willing to change the rules, then you're you're
bound by that. How do we know that? Because it says, אמר
לו נאמן עלי אבא נאמן עלי אביך נאמנים עלי שלשה רועי בקר.
amar lo ne'eman alai aba ne'eman alai avicha ne'emanim alai shlosha ro'ei
bakar. If
Michael and I have a court case and Michael says, look, normally,
you know, your father and my father wouldn't be כשר kosher to
be in a בית דין, beit din, or these, you know, these
cow herds wouldn't be כשר kosher to be in a בית דין
beit din because, you know, they're well, גזלנים gazlanim or whatever, if
not גזלנים gazlanim but other things, not עוסקים ביישובו oskim be-yishuvo anyway.
So, I don't think it's גזלנים gazlanim because wait a minute, yeah,
they're they're not בקיאין בדין. bekiin b'din. Okay, גזלנים gazlanim might not
work anyway, the רשב"ם Rashbam discusses it.
But anyway, we'll take these people that normally wouldn't be כשר, kosher,
but it's okay, I'll sign a waiver, I agree to have them
on my בית דין. beit din. So that works. You're bound by
that. So if you change the rules, if both sides sort of
like agree to change the rules, you're bound by it. So the
same is true here, so it's not a חידוש. chidush. So what's
the חידוש chidush says the גמרא? Gemara? Okay, רבי מאיר אומר יכול
לחזור בו, Rebbi Meir omer yachol lachzor bo,
Rebbi Meir says that even if you make that agreement, you can
change the rules, you're not bound by it, וחכמים אומרים אינו יכול
לחזור בו, v'Chachamim omrim eino yachol lachzor bo, and the חכמים Chachamim
say you can't change the rules. So presumably we go by the
חכמים. Chachamim. So this is just an idea that in a court
case if both sides agree, they can change the rules. Okay, so
the same is true about the שבועה. shvuah. What's the חידוש chidush
here? So the גמרא Gemara says no, הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashmalan,
this is teaching us דאיתא למחלוקת d'eita l'machloket and הלכה כדברי חכמים.
halacha k'divrei chachamim.
Number one we rule like the חכמים, Chachamim, not like רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir, that you can change the rules. But number two אתן
לך מחלוקת. etein lecha machloket. What's the point? Some want to say
that maybe it only works to change the rules if you say,
we'll let my father be on the בית דין beit din and
if he gets you off and he says you don't have to
pay, you don't have to pay. You can keep what's already in
your pocket. That's one degree of a חידוש. chidush. But can you
change the rules so much to say, my father can be on
the בית דין beit din if he says I have to pay,
I will pay? אתן לך, etein lecha,
not just that you won't have to pay me, that we can
keep things the way they are, but that their decision will be
so powerful that they'll even have the power of forcing me to
have to pay up, to even taking money away from me. So
that's there's a debate how to read when that works. So what
the גמרא Gemara is saying here is that we say to the
most extreme. If you agree to those new rules, A we rule
like the חכמים Chachamim that it works and you can't back out,
and number three it's even true even if it's to make somebody
pay. And that's the case here. Michael said, טוב, tov, take a
שבועה, shvuah, I took a שבועה, shvuah, now Michael is going to
have to pay and he's going to have to give me the
slave. So that's what we see. We rule that those are binding
and even binding in the case of אתן לך. etein lecha. Okay,
we'll end with this for now.